<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Fall 2012 RUC]]></title>
  <link href="http://winiepu.github.com/ruc12fall/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://winiepu.github.com/ruc12fall/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-26T15:30:52+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://winiepu.github.com/ruc12fall/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[ruc]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Consumer and firm's behavior]]></title>
    <link href="http://winiepu.github.com/ruc12fall/blog/2012/09/26/consumer-firm-behavior/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-26T15:17:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://winiepu.github.com/ruc12fall/blog/2012/09/26/consumer-firm-behavior</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have finished introducing basic concepts, topics and business cycles in Macroeconomics. Hope all
of you are interested in this subject now. This week I will talk about consumer and firm&#8217;s
behavior. I found an <a href="http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/fandd/basics/bigsmall.htm">article</a> about
the divide between Micro and Macro. Please read it after the lecture.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ricardian model]]></title>
    <link href="http://winiepu.github.com/ruc12fall/blog/2012/09/19/ricardian-model/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-19T10:25:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://winiepu.github.com/ruc12fall/blog/2012/09/19/ricardian-model</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have finished chapter 2. I have sent hw1 and new slides to your email. Check them out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[International Econ slides 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://winiepu.github.com/ruc12fall/blog/2012/09/14/inter-slides1/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-14T10:44:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://winiepu.github.com/ruc12fall/blog/2012/09/14/inter-slides1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have sent slides to your email. Check them out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Macro slides 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://winiepu.github.com/ruc12fall/blog/2012/09/14/macro-slides1/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-14T10:40:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://winiepu.github.com/ruc12fall/blog/2012/09/14/macro-slides1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have sent slides to your email. Check it out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Intermediate Macro syllabus]]></title>
    <link href="http://winiepu.github.com/ruc12fall/blog/2012/09/12/macro-syllabus/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-12T17:18:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://winiepu.github.com/ruc12fall/blog/2012/09/12/macro-syllabus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Course Description</em>:</p>

<p>This course is required for all undergraduate majors and for most minors in economics. It is also a
prerequisite for many other undergraduate economics courses. The purpose of this course is to
provide a formal exposition of modern macroeconomics. I will start building up from what you have
learned before and expand it; yet, the analysis will be done in a rigorous way. For this reason, the
tools you’ve learned in Intermediate Micro will prove extremely useful (I will do a small review
before using them); even though this is not a microeconomics course, you need to be sure why things
happen and to keep a clear idea of what’s going on behind all the results we get. In the end, both
graphical and mathematical analysis will be used for the exposition.  Up to now, there is no
“definite” approach to teaching an intermediate macroeconomics course. While you should be
familiar with the Keynesian model, I’ll present both the Keynesian and the Real Business Cycle
(RBC) frameworks in the course, with an emphasis on the latter. The reason is simply that the RBC
model is the workhorse of modern macroeconomics (at the research frontier).  Last, but not least, an
added goal of the course is to test important theoretical results on realworld data and examples. I
think that any Macroeconomics course should balance a strong theoretical background and empirical
analysis. Get ready to crunch some data.</p>

<p><em>Prerequisite</em>:</p>

<p>I will be constantly using results you learned in Intermediate Micro, such as the utility
maximization problem and its related topics (i.e., income and substitution effects, intertemporal
choice, labor supply, etc.). Math-wise, I will take as granted that you know how to work with
calculus (derivatives and general optimization); although the course will not be math-based, I will
be using calculus from time to time when this procedure is useful to formalize the intuition. I will
try to put emphasis on the conceptual content rather than mathematical sophistication, although the
latter is sometimes unavoidable. I will provide a handout with the basics of mathematical analysis
you need to know for the course.</p>

<p>Since you will be working with data, I will assume that you have a working knowledge of programs
that help you to organize and graph numbers, such as Microsoft Excel. From past experience knowledge
of data-handling programs like MS Excel is useful well beyond the scope of this class.</p>

<p><em>Text Books</em>:</p>

<p>Up to a few years, the traditional way of teaching intermediate macro had an emphasis on Keynesian
analysis and the IS-LM framework. Nowadays we have excellent textbooks that use the modern approach
to macroeconomics, which is based on solid microeconomic foundations in a general equilibrium
environment.</p>

<p>The book we will be using is Macroeconomics, by Stephen Williamson (3rd edition), Addison
Wesley. This textbook is required (we will be covering most of it) and should be available at online
bookstores. You are free to use the previous edition of Williamson&#8217;s book, although there may be
some minor problems with chapter numberings.</p>

<p>Although we will be following Williamson closely, you might want to review some other sources to
strengthen your understanding of the material. These (non-required) books are:</p>

<p>Macroeconomics, by N. Gregory Mankiw (6thth edition), Worth Publishers. This is a great book to strengthen your understanding of the Keynesian approach to macroeconomics.</p>

<p>Macroeconomics: A modern approach, by Robert Barro (1stst edition), Thomson South-Western. This book is somewhat similar to Williamson’s text, with an emphasis on microfoundations.</p>

<p><em>Course Requirements</em>:</p>

<p>There will be 4 homework assignments, 2 midterms and a final. Class attendance is not mandatory but is highly recommended. From past experience, students who did not attend classes on average did poorly in this class.</p>

<p><em>Exams</em>:</p>

<p>There will be two midterm exams and one final exam. The second midterm is cumulative in the sense
that the material covered builds upon heavily in the material from the first midterm. The final exam
is also cumulative, and covers all the material in the course.</p>

<p>There will be no make-up exam for the midterm (if there is a documented family or medical emergency,
the weight of the midterm will be shifted to the final).</p>

<p><em>Tentative Course Online (Preliminary, Subject to Change)</em></p>

<p>The material that will be covered is summarized below. For sure I will cover parts I through V; the
material in Part VI is optional and will be covered as a function of the remaining time and your
interest in the topics. The reference for each topic in parts I through V is in parenthesis; some
handouts will be given as a complement to the exposition in the book. I will provide additional
references for some of the topics in Part VI as needed.</p>

<p>Part I: Measurement</p>

<ol>
<li>Introduction (Chapter 1)</li>
<li>Measurement and national accounts (Chapter 2)</li>
<li>Business cycle measurement (Chapter 3)</li>
</ol>


<p>Part II: The one-period economy</p>

<ol>
<li>Microeconomic fundamentals (Chapter 4)

<ul>
<li>The utility maximization problem</li>
<li>Income and substitution effects; the Slutsky equation</li>
<li>The consumption-leisure-labor supply model</li>
<li>The firm’s profit maximization problem</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>A closed-economy one-period macroeconomic model (Chapter 5)</li>
</ol>


<p>Part III: Introduction to dynamics and economic growth</p>

<ol>
<li>The Solow growth model (Chapter 6)</li>
<li>Growth convergence (Chapter 7)</li>
</ol>


<p>Part IV: The basic two-period economy</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Microeconomic fundamentals (Chapter 8)</p>

<ul>
<li>The intertemporal choice problem</li>
<li>Income and substitution effects; the Slutsky equation</li>
<li>The firm’s profit maximization and optimal investment problem</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>A real intertemporal model with investment (Chapter 9)</li>
<li>A monetary intertemporal model (Chapter 10)</li>
</ol>


<p>Part V: Comparing the models</p>

<ol>
<li>Market-clearing models of the business cycle (Chapter 11)</li>
<li>Keynesian macroeconomics and sticky wages (Chapter 12)</li>
</ol>


<p>Part VI: Additional topics</p>

<ol>
<li>Rules versus discretion: Time consistent economic policy</li>
<li>Extending the two-period economy: An introduction to infinite-dimensional economies</li>
<li>International trade and international finance (Chapters 13, 14)</li>
<li>Money, inflation, and the Friedman Rule (Chapter 15)</li>
<li>New Keynesian models: Menu costs and sources of sticky prices</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[International Economics Syllabus Fall 2012]]></title>
    <link href="http://winiepu.github.com/ruc12fall/blog/2012/09/06/interecon-syllabus/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-06T00:07:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://winiepu.github.com/ruc12fall/blog/2012/09/06/interecon-syllabus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Course Description</em>:</p>

<p>We will study the economics of the global economy. This course consists of two parts:</p>

<p>International Trade and International Finance. First, we will analyze the causes and consequences of
international trade. We will try to answer the questions such as “Why do countries trade?” and
What do they trade?” We will also investigate who gains from the trade. We will then examine the
policy issues involved in international trade. We will analyze the motives for countries to restrict
trade and the effects of such policies on economic welfare.</p>

<p>In the second part of the course, we will move to study the basic theory of international finance
and its policy implications. Potential topics will include balance of payments, foreign exchange
market, exchange rate determination, etc.</p>

<p><em>Prerequisite</em>:</p>

<p>I will be constantly using results you learned in Intermediate Micro, such as the utility maximization problem and its related topics (i.e., income and substitution effects, intertemporal choice, labor supply, etc.). Math-wise, I will take as granted that you know how to work with calculus (derivatives and general optimization); although the course will not be math-based, I will be using calculus from time to time when this procedure is useful to formalize the intuition. I will try to put emphasis on the conceptual content rather than mathematical sophistication, although the latter is sometimes unavoidable. I will provide a handout with the basics of mathematical analysis you need to know for the course.</p>

<p>Since you will be working with data, I will assume that you have a working knowledge of programs that help you to organize and graph numbers, such as Microsoft Excel. From past experience knowledge of data-handling programs like MS Excel is useful well beyond the scope of this class.</p>

<p><em>Text Books</em>:</p>

<p>The required textbook for this course is International Economics: Theory &amp; Policy by
 Paul R. Krugman and Maurice Obstfeld, Addison Wesley, 2009.</p>

<p>International Economics by Robert C. Feenstra and Alan M. Taylor</p>

<p><em>Course Requirements</em>:</p>

<p>There will be 4 homework assignments, a final. Class attendance is not mandatory but is highly recommended. From past experience, students who did not attend classes on average did poorly in this class.</p>

<p>Tentative Course Online (Preliminary, Subject to Change)</p>

<p><em>Part I: International Trade</em></p>

<ol>
<li>Introduction and overview</li>
<li>The Ricardian Model</li>
<li>Heckscher-Ohlin Model</li>
<li>Imperfect Competition and International Trade</li>
<li>International Trade Policy</li>
<li>International Factor Movements</li>
</ol>


<p><em>Part II: International Macro</em></p>

<ol>
<li>National Income Accounting and Balance of Payments</li>
<li>Exchange Rate and the Foreign Exchange Market</li>
<li>Money, Interest Rates, and Exchange Rates</li>
<li>Price Levels, and the Exchange Rate in the Long Run</li>
<li>Output and the Exchange Rate in the Short Run</li>
<li>Fixed Exchange Rates and Foreign Exchange Intervention</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
